[Music]
consider an
x by x square a joined
with an a by x rectangle
together these shapes enclose a total
area
of x squared plus a times
x now separate the a by x rectangle
cut it in half along the side with
length a and attach the two resulting
smaller rectangles to adjacent sides of
the square
like this these three rectangles now
almost fill a larger square with side
length x
plus a over two however
there is a smaller a over two by a over
two square
missing from the lower right corner
therefore
we see the original enclosed area is
quantity x plus a over two squared
minus the quantity a over two squared
converting x squared plus ax
to the form x plus a over 2 squared
minus a over 2 squared
is called completing the square